Okay. Did you see it? There was
something
there. How do you make a film about
something the characters refuse to talk
about? In relationships, pain that goes
unagnowledged can sometimes form an
object that obscures our vision, making
it difficult to see each other for who
we really are and communicate. But how
do you make a movie about something the
characters themselves don't understand?
This is what Sentimental Value, the
latest film from Wim Trier, who you
probably know for The Worst Person in
the World, explores with beautiful
subtlety and nuance. The film uses deaf
cinematography and a metaodern narrative
to bring you into the experience of this
family as they try to connect and
confront their shared pain. I was lucky
enough to get to see it premiere this
week at the Can Film
Festival where it instantly became one
of the favorites of the fest and a movie
which I'm confident will be one of the
best of 2025. This is
Can one of the largest film festivals in
the world. And I'm here for 12 days to
watch what will be some of the most
notable movies of 2025. For example,
last year Anora won the grand prize here
at CAN the Palador before going on to
later sweep the Oscars. So being here is
a great opportunity to get a preview of
the year to come in
cinema. Can is a massive sprawling
festival. There are 22 films in
competition competing for the grand
prize which this year included some of
my most anticipated films of the year
like Ari's Edington, Wes Anderson's The
Phoenician Scheme, Kelly Reichart's The
Mastermind, and Richard Linklater's film
Nouvo Vog. On top of that, there's five
other categories with a total of 51
other films that screen as well as
screenings of classic movies. It's
literally impossible to see it all. To
attend can is to enter a whirlwind of
international cinema. You try to see as
much as you can, scrambling to eat and
sleep in the moments in between. But for
every screening you attend, it feels
like there are two more incredible films
that you missed. So join me as I spend 2
weeks watching the best of world cinema.
And let's talk about which of the films
from can I think you'll want to watch in
the year
ahead. This video is brought to you by
Movie. Watch a curated selection of
great movies from past can festivals
with your free trial at
movie.com/toomasflight. In a few hours,
I'm going to go into the Aryster film
Edington. I'm excited to
see what it's like. Is it gonna be my
favorite film this year
or going into the festival, there were a
lot of movies from great directors that
I was very excited to see, including
Lynn Ramsay's Die My Love and Julia
Dorno's Alpha. But while I enjoyed
these, many of my most anticipated films
didn't end up blowing me away, and a few
left me wanting slightly more. The
biggest of these was probably Edington
from Ary Aster. Aster is one of my
favorite horror directors and has a
unique directorial voice. So, I thought
maybe his panic attack co era satire
would end up being one of my favorites
of the festival. When I walked out of
the screening, the reaction from the
other critics I spoke with was pretty
mixed. Some hated it, and I definitely
wasn't in that camp, but I had a hard
time unabashedly loving it either. Art
takes us on a tour through co era
America using the lens of a small town
western. Some of the European critics
there wanted to know what the Americans
at the festival thought of the film. And
we expressed the discomforting reality
that while much of the movie is
certainly over the top, by the standards
of America in the last 5 years, it it
doesn't feel that unrealistic. What the
movie succeeds at is holding up a mirror
or two and capturing the feeling of the
social media fueled polarization that it
feels like has set the tone for life
here the past 5 years. There are some
fantastic performances including I think
Austin Butler again stealing the show
with a fairly small part. And like with
Bo is afraid, Aster again captures the
anxietyprovoking feeling of being
trapped within insanity with no escape.
I wrote this film in a state of fear and
anxiety about the world. Where I was
left wanting more though was where Aster
takes us from here. There may be a
cathartic value in simply reliving COVID
era Americana absurdism, but if I'm
going to relive that time, or if it's
going to be milked for all its horror
and entertainment value, in some ways, I
hope to be left with some new insight or
understanding of what's being depicted.
There's definitely a value to an artist
holding up a mirror to things without
providing a way out. And maybe part of
the horror here is that there doesn't
seem to be a clear way out in reality
either. But as I thought about the film
and discussed it with others, I couldn't
help feeling like I wanted more and
thinking that maybe there was a missed
opportunity here for something more
profound. That said, if you're a fan of
Bo is Afraid or Aster's work in general,
this will probably be one of the most
talked about movies this year. So check
it out so you can formulate your own
opinion and be an informed member of
that
discussion. Let's shift our attention
though to the movies I'm excited to
recommend. The unfortunate thing about
end of the year lists is that by the
time I mention the films, most of them
have come and gone from theaters, which
is often the best place to see them. So,
the big benefit of going to a festival
like can is getting to catch some of
these lesserk known but incredible films
so that I can recommend them to you in
time for you to catch them as they're
coming out. I watched over 20 movies,
way too many to talk about here. So, if
you want to see my full rundown, you can
find that on my newsletter or Patreon,
which I'll link to in the description
below. I came to can looking for movies
that would surprise me, transport me to
a new place, be emotionally evocative,
showcase innovative film making, or just
be wildly entertaining. Here are the
movies that checked one or more of those
boxes for me, which I think you should
check out. Let's start with some
honorable mentions. Urchin was the
directorial debut from actor Harris
Dickinson, who I first caught wind of at
can a few years ago when I watched the
triangle of sadness. I'm always
fascinated to see actor to director
transitions. They don't always work, but
this one definitely did for me. I really
enjoyed Urchin. It feels very Safy
Brothers inspired, but Dickinson still
manages to find his own unique voice
beyond that. It follows a kind of hard
to love character as he tries to get his
life together, deal with addiction, and
get off the streets. But I found myself
rooting for him and wanting him to
succeed anyway. I'm excited to watch it
again and I left hoping that Dickinson
continues to direct and develop his
directorial voice. I missed Scarlett
Johansson's debut Elanor the Great,
although I heard it was good, but I did
catch Kristen Stewart's the chronology
of water. This is based on a memoir from
Lydia Yucknovich and it has a fractured
visually poetic style that follows the
lead played powerfully by Image and
Poots as she tries to move through and
deal with her traumatic childhood. While
the directing is a tad heavy at moments,
I was impressed that Stuart did not play
it safe at all. While a lot of movies I
saw at the festival really captured me
at the beginning and then felt like they
faltered by the third act, this movie
did the opposite. I was unsure of it at
first, but by the end it had really won
me over and it was one of my favorite
endings of the festival, one that really
resonated with me emotionally. I also
really enjoyed The Love That Remains, a
new film from Hilner Palmson, the
Icelandic filmmaker who directed
Godland, one of my favorite movies of
2023. This movie is very different from
that one. It's a quiet pastoral
contemplation of nature, beauty, family,
and love. There are three children, a
dog, some chickens, a mother who's an
artist, and a father who works on a
fishing boat. And not a whole lot
happens. We follow their quiet,
beautiful life, and the parents work
through a separation. The focus here is
beautiful lingering moments of nature,
family interaction, the stuff we often
let pass us by way too easily. It was a
soothing movie to watch. Even its more
dramatic moments were kind of surreal,
funny, or almost endearing. I look
forward to watching it again when I need
a break from the break neck pace of life
or just to be reminded of the beauty I
don't want to take for
granted. Cinema as metaodern mythology.
cinema as fairy tale. All of film
history packed into a single film before
blowing it all to pieces at the end.
That's the incredible ambition of
Chinese filmmaker Begon's resurrection,
which was easily the most insanely
stylistically bold film I saw at the
festival. It takes us through a series
of dreams dreamt by a monster whose
insides contain reels of film. It starts
as an expressionistic silent film
evocative of early German works and then
evolves with each new dream becoming
film noir melodrama and culminating in a
stunning one-take scene that traverses
street light and rained alleyways on New
Year's Eve. The ultimate meaning and
plot of each dream individually and then
their meaning collectively was basically
indecipherable to me, at least on first
watch. I'm not sure how much of this to
attribute to lack of sleep and cultural
barrier and how much is just intentional
dream logic, but given that the film
pretty explicitly tells you you're
watching a series of dreams, I think the
bewildering quality is very intentional.
Besides not really being able to make
sense of it, though, in terms of story,
I was caught up in the film. It made me
feel something, even if that something
was just the power that bold imagery and
cinema can hold on its own without plot.
Cinema speaks even without words. And
sometimes our desire to understand story
logically makes us overlook that power.
Resurrection continually thwarts your
interpretive capacity but still captures
your imagination. But ironically, it was
a film that by the end felt like it left
me more awake to the reality of cinema,
to the theater I was sitting in and the
fleeting finite nature of it
all. Michael Camino. Definitely the most
entertaining screening of the festival
for me was the premiere of Michael
Cavino's new film Splitzville. The
audience, which included Jason Mimoa,
Ari, and Shawn Baker, truly loved this
well-crafted romantic comedy about two
couples in a sort of love triangle. I'm
not exaggerating when I say the laughter
was uporious. At the end of the
premiere, after the applause died down,
Cavino said this. We need to keep making
cinematic comedies for Tan, plain and
simple. And I think cinematic comedy is
a great way to describe this movie
because it's not just about funny
dialogue or comedic timing and
performances. There are jokes that are
made with editing, with cinematography,
and especially with stunt choreography.
This movie has probably the funniest
comedic fight scene I've ever seen. I
kind of thought maybe slapstick was like
a dead art form, but it's alive and
well, at least in this. It's not just
that, though. There's wit and there's
genuine drama. I really was rooting for
these characters. I can't guarantee if
you go see this in a theater, everyone
will be dying of laughter as much as
they were here because canned has some
of the most expressive audiences that
I've ever experienced. But it's worth
checking out in a theater just on the
off chance that you do get that
experience because this was a reminder
of how fun it can be just to laugh
together at a film.
We just walked out of a very bleak
Russian dark comedy. Do you think it was
like uh it definitely had comedic
elements. Yeah.
It's basically a film about this lawyer
who goes on this mission through the
bureaucracy of Dalinist Russia. And then
I don't want to spoil anything, but
let's just say
it goes slowly. It goes very
slowly. Now, let's get to my true
favorites. the best of 2025. I flew in
overnight, barely got any sleep, went
straight to a screening of 2,000 m to
Andria. The very first film I saw was
easily the most intense. Director
Mistlav Shernov won best documentary for
his last film, 20 days in Marupole. This
is a brutal and unflinching look at
combat, why these soldiers fight, and
how they try to find meaning within this
hellish landscape. It's an incredibly
relevant account of the invasion of
Ukraine, which will give you a better
understanding of what's happening there.
But the story is also grounded within
the timeless story of violent conflict
over land that's been happening for
thousands of years. I find it a little
disheartening that people will flock to
see a movie like Civil War, which
attempts and I think fails to try to
showcase the value of war journalism.
while the actual truly important works
of that journalism will often go
overlooked. I think this will probably
be one of the most significant
documentaries of the year and it's one I
highly recommend you check out.
Although, fair warning, it is graphic
and not for the faint of heart. In
direct contrast to that is one of the
movies I saw at the fest that was just
genuinely a fun time. Richard Linklater
is one of those directors I encountered
when I was young who introduced me to
just how much freedom is available in
the form of cinema. When you're just
willing to playfully explore, why not
break all the rules? It's an energy he
borrows directly from the French new
wave filmmakers. So, I found it fitting
that he chose to tell the story of the
making of Gdar's Breathless, probably
the most influential film from the
French New Wave. The pitch perfect
casting, thorough research, and period
filmmaking make it feel like you're
really watching something from the
1950s. Richard Link later said in the
press conference that he explicitly
wasn't trying to make a Gdard film, but
a film that felt like it was shot by one
of his contemporaries at the time, that
he didn't want the movie or the
characters in the film to feel like they
understood the significance and
influence of what they were doing. And I
think that's the way to approach the
film. A lot of people will want this to
be something more than it is, which is
essentially a Richard Linklater hangout
movie about making a film set in the
1950s. Watching this at can in an
audience of about a thousand critics was
a wild and interesting way to experience
the film. It literally opens with scenes
of critics attending can. You could
almost see this as pandering except for
the fact that Gdard looms so large as a
figure for many critics that making a
movie about him which actually makes
those people happy is quite the
challenge. And I find it really funny
how precious a lot of critics are with
Gdard. One critic leading the screening
said he's rolling in his grave and I'm
kind of like I don't know let him roll.
It's good exercise. And besides Gdar's
whole thing was being totally unprecious
about cinema. So why should we be so
precious in trying to protect him as a
figure? To be clear, I don't think the
movie is disrespectful. I think critics
are just hard to please. I doubt this
will have a huge audience outside of
committed film lovers, but I really see
this becoming an enduring cult classic.
It sounds like it's going to be out this
October. I'm up here on the press
terrace near the end of the second day.
So far today, I picked up a last minute
ticket to a press screening of Masha
Shalinsk's second film, Sound of
Falling. And this was a haunting,
disconnected, sort of existential
horror, generational coming of age
story. Very poetic, evocative of like
Tarovski, even David Lynch in some ways.
I found it very beautiful and arresting.
One that I feel like I need to see again
to really get a handle on. This movie is
asking you to kind of sit with it in a
quiet space, which you know this is not
a quiet space. It looks very peaceful,
but trust me, it's
not. I was trying to like write down
some thoughts about it myself and it
felt like you have this one single soul
that's fragmented over these different
points of consciousness and they can
all perceive like little bits of itself
but none of it is complete. None of it
kind of coheres together but like in the
whole of it like there is some kind of
image that starts to form. The sound and
production design are incredible. And I
think this had my favorite
cinematography of the festival. And
within all this, it explores oppression,
objectification, unhappiness, and death
through the interior experience of the
women at the center of the story. I
spoke with Louise Hayer, one of the
actors from the film, and asked her if
the beautiful poetic dreamlike quality
of the film was felt while they were
making it. and she said she could feel
it even in reading the script,
describing how the script talked about
the feeling of looking at the sun with
your eyes closed. Something that the
movie actually manages to capture. It's
perhaps a little too challenging in
Avantgard to be a huge awards contender
this year, but it's hauntingly beautiful
and will linger in the minds of those
who choose to seek it out. I don't think
it has a release date yet, but I was
excited to see that movie picked it up,
so hopefully we'll get a chance to watch
it very soon. Can is maybe the only
place I would hold a schedule like this.
I was up till 3:00 in the morning. It's
7:00 a.m. right now. I'm walking down to
see a movie at 8 and then I'll probably
honestly come home and sleep for a
while. Day five, I think.
Part of what I love about the festival
and international film in general is
when a filmmaker gets to introduce you
to their country through their own
perspective.
You know what? Go and wear your clothes.
You are following me to Legos today.
This is done with a lot of warmth and
care and attention to craft by Akenola
Davies Jr. whose debut film, My Father's
Shadow, became the first Nigerian film
to premiere at Can. The movie is set
with an election crisis as the backdrop,
but the core narrative surrounds two
brothers who get the rare opportunity to
spend the day with their father. It's a
beautiful, touching film, really
well-made. I highly recommend it. It
doesn't have a release date yet, but it
was also picked up by Movie. And I'd
love to see this be an awards contender
for later this
year. Not many directors have been
banned from film making, imprisoned for
their film making, and then continued to
work secretly and illegally in spite of
that. That's what Iranian filmmaker
Yafar Pana has been doing for almost a
decade in order to defy government
censorship. His films during this period
of clandestine filmm have been
inventive, often pseudo documentaries
that make incisive political commentary
while still somehow continuing to be
entertaining, often maintaining a sort
of playful exploration. I think Yafar
Pana is one of the boldest, bravest and
most interesting filmmakers working
right now. I very recently fell in love
with his work and I found it was just an
accident his latest film which played at
can this year and ended up snagging the
palador to be one of his most compelling
recent films. In many ways, without so
much of a meta layer, it's a more
straightforward narrative from Panay
than we've been used to, but its
political statement feels bolder and
more provocative. It's about a man who
recognizes and then kidnaps a member of
the regime's secret police who tortured
him and ruined his life years ago. It
becomes an almost dark comedy of errors
about how the kidnapping proceeds, but
it still thoughtfully and dramatically
explores the central moral dilemma
before delivering one of the most
powerful and sharpest endings of the
festival. I'm on day seven of the
festival now and I'm starting to think
about not just the individual movies I'm
watching, but what these movies are
representing, what the future of cinema
looks like. The future of cinema is
international. you're seeing so many
beautiful films from so many different
countries just drives home the fact that
this is a world art and the best
upandcomers now are not in the United
States and the United States will will
continue to be you know a dominant
player in the film and cinema scene for
a long time to come but uh they're not
going to be just at the top of the
hierarchy indefinitely forever. I love
this about can and I think it's
something that we should embrace and not
try to run away from. I think we should
embrace cinema as a world art because I
think that's where the future of the art
form
lies. A father wanders through a desert
rave searching for his daughter.
Having no luck, he and his son band
together with some experienced ravers
for a cross desert journey to find
her. There's little plot to speak of in
Sirat, or at least what plot I could
speak of would spoil too much, but I
don't need to talk about it because
what's impressive here is not so much
the plot as the atmosphere and
construction of the film, which I was
completely enraptured by. The film opens
with an epigraph that defines Sirat as
the bridge between heaven and hell,
which is thinner than a hair and sharper
than a sword. This might seem initially
disconnected from lingering shots of
trucks driving through the dusty swirl
of the desert set to pulsating
baselines, but that journey eventually
brings this well-performed group of
misfits and us into a confrontation with
that Surat. I found myself really
invested in these characters despite
their minimal development. And even
though I watched this very early in the
fest, I find myself still thinking about
these characters now. I also found the
use of electronic dance music really
interesting here. The film taps into its
translike, spiritually evocative
character that rave culture values it
for. There are these people who go into
the desert or a warehouse, take drugs,
and dance for hours to the pulsating
beat of a drum in search of a loss of
self. And this movie kind of asks us,
what happens if that sense of loss
becomes real? How do you grapple with
that? It makes some very bold narrative
choices which will definitely lose some
people. But this movie momentarily
crushed a piece of my soul, swept me up,
transported me to somewhere that felt
completely new and otherworldly before
grounding me again at the end with a
scene that felt like it placed
everything within a larger context. I
can't wait to see this again in
theaters, especially with a good sound
system. It's one of my favorites of the
festival, a strong contender for being
one of my favorite films of the year. It
doesn't have a release date yet, but I'm
hoping it will drop before too long so
that I can go on this journey
again. While Sentimental Value didn't
have the youthful punch of The Worst
Person in the World, that felt totally
intentional. This is a much more mature,
nuanced, developed drama about
communication, art, and what it means to
have a home. Stellan Scarsgard is
magnetic as an aging director who's
trying to make a movie about his mother
that stars his daughter. But this isn't
a movie about filmmaking that just
exists as a backdrop that really wants
us to try to understand these characters
and how they manage or fail to connect
with each other. This entire cast is
great and has some of the more subtle
nuance performances that I've seen in a
while. And Trier's direction is
confident and incredibly precise without
ever feeling stuffy or constrained. The
ending of this had me glued to the
screen, really aching for these
characters to find what they're looking
for. There isn't a set release date yet,
but Neon picked it up, so I'll be
excited to see it for a third time once
it comes out.
[Music]
We're in the home stretch here. I'm
exhausted. There's only one day left.
You can tell the critics are getting
tired. This afternoon, I'm going to
watch Barry Lyndon. They're screening a
new uh restored print. It feels like
that'll be a nice break for my brain to
watch something that I'm not having to
evaluate or really think about as I
watch it. And then after that, we have
the Kelly Reichart film Mastermind. And
then we've pretty much wrapped it for
the
festival. So, I'm sure at this point
you're wondering, how and when do I get
to be able to see these movies? The
thing about a festival like can is
movies come here before they have
distribution. They come here to get
distribution a lot of times and so they
might not come out for months or
sometimes a year or more. Luckily, one
of the distributors that's picked up a
lot of great films this year is Movie.
Movie is an online
handcurated streaming service that has
been sponsoring my channel for years,
and it's cool to see them embrace the
production and distribution of some
really incredible films, including Kelly
Reichart's The Mastermind, which I just
saw last night. I thought it was a
really beautiful, understated film, and
it'll be out on Movie eventually for you
to watch. movie will also be
distributing The Sound of History, which
was one of the incompetition films here,
and two of my other favorites from the
festival, Sound of Falling and My
Father's Shadow. And if you don't want
to wait for those movies to come out,
they have a curated selection of great
films from past can festivals available
right now that you can check out. You
can also see big players from last
year's can, like The Substance on Movie.
Check them out. Sign up at
movieby.com/toomasflake. that extended
30-day free trial. And thanks again to
Movie for making this video
possible. Say goodbye to the people
tone. Bye. Till next time. See you next
year.